{
  "reference_number": "9705",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "However, I think some companies/areas of our economy may only be able to achieve low emissions rather than zero, so I think an\n overall balance is important. Ensuring that real change is made towards our goals, but allowing for some leeway in what may be a\n realistic expectation from some industries/companies. I guess 'net zero' means an overall result - not per business."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Advice from the Climate Change Commission. Any industries such as transport, forestry, farming, manufacture, etc. that are likely to\nhave high impacts on emissions production/reduction. I think a holistic approach is important - looking at all aspects &\n\nconsiderations."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I think it is important to have very good science advice; as well as having a balanced expertise group, so that advice is practical and\nsensible. Commissioners with expertise but not vested interests."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I think a risk assessment and adaption plan are important as things are always changing and so priorities in responding to the effects\n\nof climate change will need to change. In some areas the effects of flooding may become extreme; perhaps we might need to reduce\nthe use of petrol, etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I'm very keen to see this bill passed so we in NZ are doing our bit to meet the goals of the world as well as making our own country\n\nmore efficient and greener in all we do. I had some reservations about the description 'carbon zero', despite the word 'net' being\nadded as we need carbon and carbon dioxide as part of life on the planet. Which is why I think it is important to have balanced\n\nscientific advice as part of the work done to make the changes needed. It is important to act now and to focus the thinking of\nindustries towards reduced emissions (and not just trade units to avoid real change). I was recently disappointed to hear that\n\nalthough Wellington now has a new bus fleet, I understand many buses are still run on diesel - why are they not electric! I heard it was\nbecause of cost. Is it possible that the government may provide funding to assist companies to make changes that are better for the\nenvironment but which they have avoided because of the cost? Also I understand changes are happening in the farming sector - cool\n\nto read about Ngai Tahu Farming, but I would like to see a strong encouragement, and possible financial support, for diversification in\nfarming so dairying is not expanded to a huge extent. I am also keen on the government taking greater action in the area of waste\n\nreduction, although this is perhaps not the focus of this submission. Thank you for the opportunity to comment."
    }
  ]
}
